the last part of this lecture is about
paging now this is the most advanced
memory allocation mode and it completely separates
logical from physical memory we are not going
to discuss virtual memory today so if it's only
about paging it's not really more complicated than
segmentation if you understood segmentation
then you will also understand paging so make
sure everything is clear about the segmentation
part when that is okay then let's move to paging
so this is a mechanism to separate or let's say
manage disjointly physical addresses from logical
ones and it doesn't need
to allocate contiguous portions of memory for the
process the process can be completely scattered
around the memory into smaller units which are the
pages it's basically what is used in many modern
operating systems and as we will see especially in
the next lecture it really requires cooperation
between the operating system and the hardware
the idea is pretty simple instead of dividing
a process into segments we divide a process
into pages and a page is smaller than a
segment it's not the entire data section
it's usually a power of two in terms
of number of addresses we will see this
so the logical memory it's divided into pages
and the physical memory it's also divided into
units these ones are called frames and
each frame is equal to a page so the size of a
frame is the same as the size of a page you
keep stuff on the disk organized into pages
and when you want to load a certain process into
memory a program into memory and start a process
then what you do is that you take
your physical memory which has
which is divided into frames and you place
the pages of the process inside the frames
you don't need to put them one after the other
in a contiguous fashion or order you can just put
the pages into the frames the way you want
and what you need to do then is to keep
track of where each page is located so what
is the frame that contains each page in this
example we have a process it requires four pages
from zero to three it means we need four frames
this is how the pages are loaded
into the frames in this example
so what you do is that you maintain a page
table this is the operating system of course
the number of rows you have in this table
is equal to the number of pages you have in
the process each row refers to a page and
the content is the frame where you can find
that page so page zero is row zero and it's frame
one so if you go to frame one you have page zero
page one is row one on the second row and it's
frame four you go inside frame four and you have
page one and so on now when the CPU needs
to read or write uh something from the memory
the idea is similar to what we had before
with segmentation, this is why I'm saying
that it's not completely different from
segmentation you need to specify
the page you want to access and then within the
page the offset what is nice though is
that this specifying the page and inside the
page the address can be done very efficiently in
a single operation so the time complexity
is O(1) just by translating in a certain way
the logical address of the process into page and
offset so how does the CPU know which page
it should access we said before the process thinks
that he has a range of addresses that goes from 0 to
a certain limit so when it says i want to access
address 100 how do we compute in which page
and what is the offset of others 100 if we are
using pages well this is how you do it so I'm
going a bit rapidly here but then check the slides and
and try it out yourself if the size of the page
or the frame they have the same size is 2 power
n and the logical space you need for the process
is 2 power m and then you take your address in
binary of course the first m minus n bits indicate
the page the remaining one indicate the offset
so you can translate the binary address into
page and offset just like this let's look
at the example so here we have a process it's
four pages each page has four addresses we have
the page table and we have the physical memory
the page size is two power two okay so n is equal
to two the logical space is two power four so
m is equal to four because as you can see we
need in this case four pages for a total of
16 addresses to maintain the processing memory so
what is the physical address of logical address
seven well you take seven you put it in binary
and then you take the prefix which is in this case
the first two bits to compute what is the page
and the last bits to compute what is the offset
this is saying that is page one offset three
let's see page one if you go in the page table and
it says that it's the sixth frame so you do six
times four because the size of each frame is four
you add three which is the offset so the
physical address is 27 and if you go to
27 you will find here h which is what
you want for address 7
try the example out yourself now I
cannot cover it too much in detail
it would take a lot of time but if you try
yourself with a piece of paper you will see that
it's not that complicated now as always we have
trade-offs the good thing with paging is that
there is no external fermentation if you need to
load n frames and you have sorry n pages and you
have n free frames then it's okay you can place
each page in a frame even if these frames are not
contiguous independently of where they are on the
other hand you end up having internal fragmentation
you need to use at least one frame for a page
for each page of the process and it might be that
the process does not really require a full page or
maybe it requires three point something pages so
on average half of the last page you need for
the process might be wasted of course if you
want to minimize internal fragmentation you can go
for smaller pages but you will have more overhead
you will have a larger table to maintain you can
also go for larger pages so you have less overhead
the page table is smaller it takes less space but
of course then you end up with more fragmentation